With her death, Asseylum Vers Allusia, loyal
countryman and beloved family member,
誠実なる同胞であり　我が愛すべき家族
アセイラム·ヴァース·アリューシアは
has revealed the truth to us.
その死を以って我々に真実を伝えてくれた
Through her pious act,
she has opened our eyes.
その敬虔なる行いによって我々を目覚めさせてくれた
We are meting out justice. The Earth
has spat upon our good faith,
これは正義の行使である
我らの正義を踏み躙り　増長を重ね
heaped insult upon insult,
and now committed this atrocity!
暴虐を尽くす地球への天罰である
This is divine retribution
brought down upon them!
今日　我々ヴァース帝国は地球に対し　宣戦布告を行う
Today, the Vers Empire
declares war against Earth!
All clear in Block 63B.
63-Bブロック　異常ありません
All clear in Block 63C.
63-Cブロック　異常ありません
There's no sign that he has
escaped from the castle!
城から逃げた形跡は無い　必ず探し出せ
Track him down!
Yes, sir!
はっ
Damn that boy... How dare he use the
audience chamber without permission?
奴め　勝手に謁見の間を使うとは
When he's found,
execute him on the spot!
見つけ次第処刑せよ
Abide a moment, Count Cruhteo.
待たれよ　クルーテオ卿
Milord Saazbaum.
ザーツバルム卿
He is the son of Dr. Troyard.
そやつはトロイヤード博士の息子
I wish to question him regarding
his father's Aldnoah research.
アルドノアの研究について　問い質したい事がある
Might I trouble you
to take him alive?
生きたまま　捕らえてくれるか
All right... Please tell me
what happened after that.
それでは　続きを教えてください
Tell me about the orange Kataphrakt
that Sir Vlad had been pursuing.
ブラド卿が追っていた　オレンジ色のカタフラクトの事
君が見る夢は　古いインクで紙に書いた祈りのよう
小さなその手が　縋るものも　今はまだ何処にも無い
それでも君の行く道を
奇麗なものは奇麗なままで　守り続けたいと思うよ
空と水が星を染めて
淡く虹を描いて散って
眩しい夜　君が歌う
声は何処まで届くのだろう
憧れの住まう蒼い星のひかり
ただ僕らは恋をして
たったひとつの未来の為に
今の全て奏でてみる
飛び立つよ　まだ暗い空へ
誠実なる同胞であり　我が愛すべき家族
アセイラム·ヴァース·アリューシアは…
Grandfather... Why?
お祖父様　どうして
A formal declaration
of war, huh?
正式に宣戦布告か　休戦するって話だったのに
Just when we heard there was going
to be a cease-fire, too.
The war never stopped.
ずっと戦争は続いていたんだ
Lt. Marito...
鞠戸大尉
We all pretended not to
notice, that's all.
それを皆で知らない振りしていただけだ
Just like the old fart said, that princess'
death opened our eyes to the truth.
その爺が言う通り
あのお姫さんが死んで皆の目を覚ましてくれたって訳だ
That isn't true! I...
違います　私は…
Princess Asseylum has
no desire for war!
アセイラム姫は　争いなど望んでいません
地球とヴァースの友好の架け橋になろうとしたのです
She tried to act as a bridge of friendship
between Earth and Vers!
And she ended up being
the spark that set it off.
そして　まんまと火種になった
This is what they've
always dreamed of.
ずっと狙ってたんだよ奴ら
Some righteous cause that would
let them pull out all the stops.
大手を振って暴れられる大義名分を
Are you saying that the Martians
sacrificed their own princess?
火星人がお姫様を生贄にしたって言うんですか
Everyone, your attention, please!
全員注目　一同ブリーフィングルームに集合
Everyone assemble in
the briefing room!
What's up, Yuki?
どうしたの　ユキ姉
Please address me as
Warrant Officer Kaizuka.
界塚准尉って呼びなさい
We're now officially at war
with them, too.
こっちも正式に　戦争する事になったの
As of right now, you are drafted
into service as soldiers.
これより　あなた方を兵士として召集します
That means that you are to adhere
to military rules and regulations,
軍法と軍規を遵守し　命令に従って任務を果たす義務が生じます
and are now obligated to carry out whatever
duties you are ordered to perform.
今まで習った事を無駄にせず　勇気を持って戦いに赴き
I look forward to seeing you
put all that you have learned to good use,
go into battle
with courage in your hearts,
and come into your own as warriors who
safeguard the peace and order of Earth.
地球の平和と秩序を守る戦士として　活躍する事を期待します
This ship will now resupply and make
repairs at Tanegashima Base.
我が艦はこれより　種子島基地で補給及び修理を行います
Afterwards, we will most likely
head for United Earth HQ in Russia.
その後　ロシアの地球連合本部に向かう事になるでしょう
All right, everyone, man your
stations immediately.
それでは各員　直ちに配置に着いてください
That is all. Dismissed.
以上　解散です
Soma Yagarai, age 28. My specialties are
surgery and psychosomatic medicine.
耶賀頼蒼真　28歳　専門は外科と心療内科
If you ever need counseling,
my door is always open.
カウンセリングなら　何時でもいらしてください
Thank you for your help. We can
use all the doctors we can get.
ご協力感謝します
So you see, my big sister Seylum has been too
sick to go to school for the longest time.
それで　セラムお姉ちゃんはずっと病気で学校には通えなかったの
If you'll excuse me, then.
Oh, is that so?
そうなの
Isn't that right, Your Highness?
ですよね　姫様
Y-Yes!
あ　はい
That is why Her Highness never
received any military training.
だから姫様は　教練を受けていないし
She is far too frail
to be a soldier.
体が弱くて兵隊さんにはなれないの
Oh...
そう
I, on the other hand,
can pilot a Kat!
でも　私ならカットの操縦くらいできるわ
When you're all grown up,
please do, okay?
じゃ　じゃあ　大きくなったらお願いね
I will! 'Bye, now!
うん　それじゃあね
Why do you call your sister
"Your Highness"?
でも　どうしてお姉さんなのに姫様なの
えっ　セラムお姉ちゃんは私の大切なプリンセスだから
B-Because to me, Seylum
is my beloved princess!
P-Please forgive my
familiar tone, Milady.
ご無礼失礼いたしました
That's quite all right, thank you.
いいえ　ありがとう
And what about you?
あなたは
How old are you? Everyone who had military
training in high school is being drafted.
おいくつ
公立高校で教練を受けた者には召集が掛かってますよ
I was kept out of school...
for family reasons.
家庭の事情で　学校には
I see. Well, even if you're not
fighting at the front,
そう　でも前線でなくとも　後方で手伝える事はたくさんあります
there are plenty of things
you can help with at the rear.
If you like, you could even support
everyone as a volunteer.
希望すれば　志願兵として皆を支える事もできますよ
Don't you want to do your part to
defend Earth from the Martians?
あなたも火星人から地球を守るために　働きませんか
Why am I a maintenance worker
instead of a pilot?!
何でパイロットじゃなくて整備員なんだよ
You did flunk piloting, Calm..
だってカームは操縦赤点じゃん
Mechanics are just as crucial to the war.
Without them, the Kats won't work.
整備だって立派な戦争よ
整備員が居ないと　カットは動かないんだから
How am I supposed to waste those
guys if I'm stuck in the hangar?!
格納庫に居たんじゃ　あいつらをぶっ飛ばせねえだろ
Hey, don't be so gung-ho.
まあ　そう気張るなって
These past 15 years, no one's
seen any real action.
この15年　実戦を経験した奴は居ないんだ
Those who did are all dead.
経験した奴は皆死んだ　火星の奴らもな
On the Martian side, too.
Meaning that friend and foe alike
are all virgins, same as you.
てことは敵も味方も皆お前らと同じ童貞だ
Not all of us.
皆じゃありません
えっ　伊奈帆　お前　まさか
Inaho, are you saying you-
You lived through it, Lt. Marito.
Isn't that right?
鞠戸大尉は生き残った　そうでしょう
ああ　そっちの話ね
Oh, you mean that.
The scorebook says otherwise.
スコアブック上は違う
The Tanegashima Report
I wrote got buried.
俺が書いた種子島レポートは握り潰された
Tanegashima Report?
種子島…　レポート
15年前　ヘブンズ·フォールで崩壊した月の破片が
It's where the fragments first fell
when the Moon was destroyed
during Heaven's Fall 15 years ago.
一番最初に落ちた場所
Yeah... But something came down there
before the Moon did.
だが月より先に落ちて来た物があった
Martians.
火星の奴らだ
We went up against those monster Martian
Kataphrakts in obsolete tanks.
その火星の化け物みたいなカタフラクト相手に
俺達は時代遅れの戦車で挑み　全滅した
We were wiped out.
Right after that, the Hyper Gate
went out of control on the Moon,
その直後にハイパーゲートが暴走
Heaven's Fall was set off
by the spacetime quake,
時空震でヘブンズ·フォールが起きて
and those Martian bastards
wiped out the entire battlefield.
火星の奴らは戦場ごと…
There's no physical evidence.
物的証拠は何も無い
My report was made out to be the ramblings
of a madman written in terror.
俺のレポートは恐怖で書き立てた妄想という事になった
But it was the truth.
でも　事実でした
Mars' Kataphrakts are way beyond what
Earth's technology can produce.
火星のカタフラクトは　地球の技術を遥かに超えています
Either way, the end result
will be the same.
どっちだろうと結果は同じだ
Because Earth doesn't have
Aldnoah drives.
何せ地球にはアルドノアドライブが無いからな
Aldnoah drives...
アルドノアドライブ
Fugitive located! He's in
the Sky Carrier hangar!
逃亡者発見　スカイキャリア格納庫です
Do not let him escape.
絶対に逃すな
おのれ　どこまで私を愚弄する気だ
Damn him... How long is he going to
continue making me look the fool?
The basics are the same as the trainer...
Even with the higher output,
基本は練習機と同じ
出力が高くても　重力と地盤強度が同じなら
if gravity and surface hardness
remain the same,
its agility will only decrease to
the extent that its weight increases.
重量が増えた分だけ俊敏さが下がる…　か
I'll just have to acclimate.
慣れるしか無いな
So this is where
you were, Inaho.
いらしたのですか　伊奈帆さん
Yes.
ええ
It truly is lovely...
本当に　綺麗
Is a blue sky
that unusual to you?
青い空は珍しいですか
Yes... Are you studying?
はい
お勉強ですか
I'm brushing up. I'm not sure
how useful it will be, though.
復習を少し
でも役に立つかどうか
Why is that?
何故ですか
Because we don't
have Aldnoah.
僕らはアルドノアを持っていないから
What's this "Aldnoah" thing, anyway?
どんな物なんですか　アルドノアって
Aldnoah is technology belonging to a supercivilization
that was discovered in ancient ruins on Vers,
アルドノアは　ヴァース…
あなた方が火星と呼ぶ惑星の古代遺跡で見つかった　超文明のテクノロジー
the world your people call Mars.
The first Terran to make
contact and awaken it
それに初めて接触し　目覚めさせた地球人が
was Dr. Rayregalia Vers Rayvers,
レイレガリア·ヴァース·レイヴァース博士
my grandfather
and ruling emperor of Vers.
私のお祖父様　現ヴァース皇帝です
Aldnoah, activated after
so many eons,
遙かなる時を経て起動したアルドノアは
recognized Grandfather
as its rightful heir
お祖父様を　正統な後継者と認識し
and burned the Aldnoah activation
factor into his very genes.
アルドノアの起動因子を　お祖父様の遺伝子に焼き込んだのです
Which means that...
という事は…
Yes. The only ones with the innate ability
to activate Aldnoah are grandfather
はい　生まれながらにアルドノアを起動できるのは
お祖父様と　その子孫だけ
and his descendants.
In exchange for the knights
swearing fealty to him,
お祖父様は　騎士達に主従の契りを交わす事で
he gave them Aldnoah
and its activation factor.
アルドノアとその起動因子を貸し与えました
Using that power,
the knights created
騎士達はその力を利用して　強大な城とカタフラクトを作り
mighty castles and Kataphrakts
and ruled over the colonies.
植民地を統治しました
And now, those who settled the desolate
lands of Mars have set their eyes...
そして　荒れ果てた火星の大地を開拓した者が次に求めたのが
on Earth.
地球です
The cradle of all humanity, a land blessed
with water and air in such abundance
光を屈折し
海と空が青く見えるほどたくさんの水と空気を持つ
that they refract light to make
the sea and sky appear blue.
私達人類発祥の地
That isn't true.
それは違います
The blue sky isn't caused by diffraction, but
through the effects of Rayleigh scattering.
空が青いのは屈折じゃなくて
レイリー散乱の影響です
えっ　でも　光の屈折だとスレインが
But Slaine said it was caused
by light diffraction...
The sky is blue from Rayleigh scattering,
clouds are white from Mie scattering.
空が青いのはレイリー散乱
雲が白いのはミー散乱
Your friend was mistaken.
その人の勘違いです
Excuse me!
すみません　替わって貰ってもいいですか
Would it be okay if I took over?
You're a real go-getter, aren't you?
気合十分じゃないか
I just want to
get a feel for it.
早く慣れたくて
What did you get in Docking?
接岸の成績は
Um, A-minus... sir.
え　Aマイナス　です
When we come into port,
stand next to me and watch.
入港は傍で見ていよう
Also, take your hands
out of your sleeves.
それと　袖から手は出せ
Y-Yes, sir! Sorry, sir.
Thank you, sir.
あ　はい　すみません
ありがとうございます
Aren't we going to get uniforms?
うちらの制服は支給されないんすか
We don't have enough. I'm hoping
we can stock up at the next port.
数が足りなくてね　次の港で補充できるといいんだが
It doesn't really feel right...
これはこれで
Why go to Tanegashima, though?
でも　どうして種子島へ
I thought this area
had been sealed off.
この海域は封鎖されていたはずでは
With our intel on their
Landing Castles so spotty now,
揚陸城の情報が不確かな今
we'd like to avoid any areas
that are likely invasion targets.
侵略対象となりそうな地域は避けたい
Tanegashima is an area that was devastated so
badly that the very landscape was altered.
種子島は　ヘブンズ·フォールで地形が変わるほど
甚大な被害を被った地域だ
Even now, there is no
civilian population here.
今も民間人は住んでいない
So you think the Martians
that came down in Tokyo
東京に降りた火星人もわざわざここまで侵略の手を伸ばさないって事ですか
won't bother attacking
anything this far out?
I never thought I'd come
back here like this.
こんな形で戻って来るとはな
Isn't it a bit early for that?
まだ日は高いですよ
This isn't for me. It's for the ones
who can't drink anymore.
それは俺の分じゃない　もう飲めない奴の分だ
Like John Humeray?
ヒュームレイさん　ですか
And...
そして　これが俺の分　精進落としだ
This one is for me.
I'm jumping off the wagon.
Want a belt, Doc?
先生もやるか
I think I will.
いただきましょう
Mind if I join you?
私にも貰えますか
Capt. Magbaredge.
マグバレッジ艦長
The Tanegashima Report. I've heard
rumors about it, of course.
「種子島レポート」　噂だけ耳に入っていました
But I never once believed
it was a fabrication.
でも私は　それをデタラメだとは思っていなかった
And that's exactly why, Lt. Marito...
だからこそ鞠戸大尉
That's why I have a particular
dislike for you.
私は余計にあなたを許せない
That battle on Tanegashima...
My big brother fought in it, too.
種子島での戦闘　私の兄も参加していたんです
He was killed in action.
Murdered, rather. By you.
戦死
いえ　殺されたんですよ　あなたに
Magbaredge is the name of
the family that adopted me.
マグバレッジは　私が引き取られた里親の名です
My birth name was Humeray.
旧姓はヒュームレイ　あなたの親友は私の兄です
Your best friend was my brother.
Enemy craft above Tanegashima!
種子島上空に敵機
Anti-air combat! Take us out
to open water!
対空戦闘　外洋に出る　最大船速　面舵いっぱい
Maximum combat speed,
hard right rudder!
えっ　私
M-Me, ma'am?!
Damage report!
被害報告
Missile impact, Block 18!
No detonation!
第18ブロックにミサイルが着弾　爆発は無し
Appears to be a dud-
No, wait!
不発弾のようで
いえ…
What is it?!
どうした
It's moving... It's alive!
動いてる　生きてます
What the hell was that?!
何なのです　一体
It's coming back!
また来ます
舵が効きません
Helm not responding!
We're going to collide!
ぶつかります
All hands, brace for impact!
全艦衝撃に備えろ
Entering my territory without
so much as a by your leave?
断りも無くわらわの領地に入るとは
Such atrocious manners.
何たる礼儀知らず
I must rake you over the coals.
Rather hot ones.
灸を据えてあげましょう　うんと熱いのをね
What is it doing
this far out?
どうしてこんな遠くまで
This must be a different Martian
than the one in Tokyo.
東京とは別の火星人のようですね
Order the shipboard Kats to launch.
艦載機を出撃させてください
Friesian Platoon, launch!
フリージアン小隊　発進
Raising elevator 1.
1番エレベーター　上昇
Calm!
カーム
This one isn't powering up.
こいつ起動しない
Sorry! We're running
a systems check on that!
悪りぃ　システムチェック中だ　もう少し待ってくれ
Give us a minute!
It's kinda cramped in here...
何かきっつい…
Inaho?
伊奈帆
Force feedback
checking program, start.
フォースフィードバックチェッキングプログラム　スタート
Ejection seat functional.
IFF confirmed.
エジェクションシート正常
IFF確認
Tactical datalink, activated.
戦術データリンク　アクティベート
All systems green.
システムオールグリーン
Mustang Leader to Mustang 22.
マスタングリーダーよりマスタング22
Nao, you're in a trainer,
so you be our marksman.
なお君は練習機だから　マークスマンをお願いね
Yuki? But your arm is still-
ユキ姉　まだ腕が…
If my newbie is fighting,
I can't sit this out, can I?
新米が出るのに　私が出ないわけいかないでしょ
Warrant Officer Kaizuka!
界塚准尉
"Yuki" is fine.
ユキ姉でいいよ
Over and out!
通信終わり　以上
Unbelievable.
まったく
Mustang Leader, Warrant Officer
Yuki Kaizuka, now launching!
マスタングリーダー界塚ユキ准尉　発進します
Raising elevator 2
and vehicle elevator.
2番エレベーター及び車両用エレベーター上昇
Friesian Platoon, deploy on the bow.
Mustang Platoon, you're on the stern.
フリージアン小隊は船首　マスタング小隊は船尾に展開
All units, intercept airborne
flying weapons!
各個に飛行兵器を迎撃せよ
I almost feel sorry for you,
不幸よのう　アルドノアドライブを持たぬ劣等民族よ
you inferior race that does not
possess the Aldnoah drive.
Cower before my power,
bow down before me,
我が力に畏怖し　屈服し　絶望して死ね
and then despair and die!
Fly, my messengers!
飛べ　我が眷属達よ
Spread out! If you're clustered
too tight, you'll be sitting ducks!
広がれ　密集すると狙われるぞ
Damn, they're tough!
堅い
My fists are transformed into a single molecule.
Your bullets are useless against them.
巨大分子と化した拳　銃弾など効かぬわ
Mustang Leader to all units! AP rounds
ineffective against enemy's armor!
マスタングリーダーより各機
敵の装甲にAP弾は無効
All units, switch over
to HE rounds and attack!
HE弾に切り替えて　各個に攻撃
- R-Roger!
- Roger.
了解
Crap!
くそっ
Lt. Marito!
Where are you going?
鞠戸大尉　何処へ
I'm playing my home field again!
I can take to the field, right?
久々のホームグラウンドだ　出撃したっていいだろ
Or maybe this is
an away game...
いや　アウェイかもな
Inko, watch our back!
韻子　後ろを頼む
Roger!
了解
On your feet!
You're a sitting duck there!
早く起きて　狙われるわよ
Y-Yes, ma'am!
Sorry, Inaho! Are you okay?
はい
ごめんね伊奈帆　大丈夫
I'm fine.
大丈夫
Is this one good to go?
いけるか
Lt. Marito? No, that one's
still being tuned!
鞠戸大尉
あ　いえ　そいつまだ調整中で
But it runs, right? I just
need it to fire one shot.
動くんだろ　一発撃てればそれでいい
Get a heavy barrel ready for it!
ヘビーバレル準備頼む
Damn... it....
くそっ
Oh, come on! What the hell?!
だから　何なんだよ
Block 24 hit! Blocks 23, 24,
and 25 taking on water!
第24ブロックに被弾
23　24　25ブロック浸水っす
Evacuate the affected
blocks immediately.
当該ブロック　避難急いでください
But if we don't seal
the bulkheads, we-
でも　隔壁を閉鎖しないと
It's all right.
構いません　どうせこの船はもう終わりです
The ship is done for, anyway.
Abandon ship,
noncombatants first!
非戦闘員から退艦
揚陸艇　発進準備を急いでください
Get the landing craft
prepped for launch ASAP!
What?
何
This way, everyone!
皆さん　こっちです
Please be careful, Milady!
お気を付けください　姫様
Thank you.
Enemy unit overhead
is in a nosedive!
上空の敵機　急降下　側面からも3機接近
Three others closing in
from our flanks!
They appear to be accelerating from
a distance to build up speed!
遠距離から加速して速力を溜めているようです
It's on a collision course
with the bridge!
ブリッジ直撃コース
I have toyed with you for
long enough. Now, die!
戯れも終いだ　そろそろ死ぬが良い
Here it comes!
来ます
What happened?
何が…
Direct hit!
Next, 3 mil right!
命中
次　右3ミル
Not even HE rounds can destroy
those things' armor plating.
HE弾でもあいつの装甲を破壊する事はできない　でも…
But...
...from this range, we can use the
blast pressure to throw it off course.
この距離なら爆発で進路を逸らす事ができる
No sign of movement in
primary enemy craft!
敵機本体動き無し
Next! Left 7 mil!
次　左7ミル
Direct hit! Last!
命中　ラスト
We won't make it...
駄目
Out of ammo?
弾切れ
Captain...
艦長
This is the end.
終わりだ
What was that?!
何事
Huh? We're alive?
あれ　生きてる
That's...
あれは…
本字幕由诸神字幕组(kamigami.org)制作，仅供交流学习，禁止用于任何商业用途
日听:つっちー    翻译:mam&低音子    校对:zwx    时间轴:Maize    压制:河蟹
0　始まりにも　終わりにも　変わる光
下に向けたまま　かざすのを止めた　あの時
ALD noah
サイズの合わない　嘘ばかり並べて
見失い　自ら全てに　つまずいた
AS　照らす　影と栄
繰り返すcount　明日の零時のサイン
LIVE or DIE
見えない　光の線
文字だけで　生kill-場所捨てて
名前も居ない　そこに　答えを求めてても
風にとかした　命のRain　投げ捨てない
駆け出しのナミダ
期待も闇も終わりもいらない
ゼロになれば　裸足のphrase-1